A Guide to the Gregory-Whitmore Family Papers, 1846-1997 (bulk 1900-1923)
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Gregory-Whitmore Family Papers 1846-1997 (bulk 1900-1923)
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10754-d
This collection contains ca. 800 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library on May 14, 1997 by Arvella Embry and Page Gregory Whitmore, and Ellie Whitmore, of Minneapolis, Minnesota.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 800 items, 1846(1900-1923)1997, composed chiefly of letters from Mary Susan Gregory Whitmore (September 19, 1846 - April 4, 1923) to her sons, Harry Gregory Whitmore and Samuel L. Whitmore. There are also letters, July and August 1915, from Harry Gregory Whitmore while on his trip to California, and letters, 1914-1915, from Samuel L. Whitmore. Other items of interest include nineteenth century receipts and photographs of the Gregory family; scrapbook, 1883, of the Reunion of the Fifth Virginia Infantry and the 28th New York Volunteers, Niagara Falls; and, a two-volume travel journal kept by Harry Whitmore on his "Trip to California, Going thru the Panama Canal and Returning thru the Canadian Rockies," with transcript. The majority of Susan Whitmore's letters from 1900-1912 and 1917-1919 have transcripts available in accession #10754-c.
Sue Gregory Whitmore's letters to her sons are filled with personal, family, and local news as well as occasional references to subjects of national interest. Letters during 1900-1902 were sent to Harry Whitmore at the University of Virginia. Topics mentioned during 1900 include: seeing the children of Charles Pinckney Jones, Rector of the University (September 19); local school board meeting (October 9); the Bryan/McKinley ballots and saying that "all the niggers turned out for fear they would be disfranchised" (November 5); the Stonewall Band (November 27); and Mr. [Scott] Randolph's Wild West Party performing at Churchville on Christmas day (December 16).
During 1901 her letters mention: varioloid among the students and the Randolph party; her son's debate at college and smallpox in Charlottesville (February 3); reading His Great Self and To Have and to Hold by Mary Johnston (February 27); engineering survey corp from West Augusta to Stribling and railroad work being resumed at Bridgewater and pushed on to Mt. Solon (March 5); a report signed by J[ames]; M[orris] Page, Professor of Mathematics, University of Virginia (March 13); [John Shelton] Patton's articles in the Dispatch(March 18); the railroad being built up Mosey Creek to Mt. Solon to Dora Coal Mines (April 2); Walter Kerr petitioning the State Board of Education for the County Superintendent position (April 2); Board of Education and requirements for the appointment of the County Superintendent (April 14); the death of Rev. Bowman and reading Richard Carvel(April 22); a fire set to Little Mountain and the damage (May 5); reading Mary Johnston's Prisoners of Hope(May 13); brief story about astronomer David Todd (1855-1939) (May 26); railroad work near Mt. Solon and a dynamite explosion killing "one negro" and nearly killing Charlie Peyton (June 3); his Latin and German examinations (September 19); the new railroad being finished soon (November 5); a railroad wreck on October 24 in which several were injured, including Joseph Martin Whitmore (1823-1912) (November 4); the death of mining engineer Frazier Bell in the Bluefield mines (November 20); and a visit and tour in Lexington, her son's reports in Latin, German, Chemistry, and Geology (December 10).
Letters written in 1902 refer to various topics: Professors [ ? ] Harrison and his comment on his report, [John William] Mallet and the Chemistry examination, [William Elisha] Peters, and [Christopher] Wright at the University of Virginia (January 14); reading two Emma Southworth books Ishmael, or In the Depths and Self raised or From the Depths(January 26); the Stonewall Band; Dave Peyton, a "black man who had a farm and was janitor to Baptist church in Staunton..."; and Professor [William Elisha] Peters (February 3); reading When Knighthood was in Flower about Charles Brandon and Mary Tudor (February 23); the Good Roads Convention having a practical test on the Monticello Road on April 2 (March 16); Collins Denny (1854-1943), and Noah K[nowles] Davis (March 30); Colonel [William Elisha] Peters, Professor of Latin at the University (April 29); Professor of English Literature, [Charles William] Kent (May 14); a story of a scandal involving Marshall Burton and Miss Lineweaver; he was arrested on a Saturday for having seduced her and "Doctor Sam" [Burton] married her the following Monday (June 2).
The letters resume in September 1903 when Harry Whitmore is in McGaheysville, Rockingham County, Virginia. Topics referred to include: Captain J[ohn] H. Whitmore, Adjutant, St. Charles Military College in St. Charles, Missouri; reading The Last of the Era by John S. Wise (October 7); news of [John Shelton] Patton being elected Librarian at the University (November 16); reading Leopards' Spots by Thomas Dixon and The Virginian by Owen Wister, and John Whitmore's stable being burned (December 16). Letters continue to be sent to McGaheysville in 1904, and refer to various topics: expectations of the arrival of Rev. James Bernard Hedrick (1878-1942) (January 12); reading The Heart's Highway by "Miss Mary Walk-Ins" [Mary Eleanor Wilkins Freeman] (January 19); husband, John Addison Whitmore reading John King's Question class of Children(January 26); news of the fire in Baltimore, Maryland (February 8); reading Furry of Eagle's Nest by John Esten Cooke (February 17); reading In the Palace of the King by Marion Crawford (February 23); inquiries of the Yanceys and the Classical Department (March 1); Dr. [James Morris] Page and Prof. [William Beverley?] Stone, and W. H. H. Joyce (March 22); description of St. Charles Military College and St. Louis, Missouri, including a street car and ferry trip (March 27); Dr. [James Morris] Page delivering an address to the graduating class (March 29); wanting him to attend the Louisiana Purchase Exposition and reading The Conquerer by Gertrude Atherton (April 5).
During September 1904 through May 1905 Harry Whitmore was in "Red Hill," Albemarle County. Sue Whitmore's letter of September 15 refers to the death of her husband, John Addison Whitmore, and his last will and testament. Whitmore died on August 30, 1904, of tuburcular consumption, at "Brook Hill." Other topics include: attending the Woman's Foreign Missionary Society in Staunton, and problems concerning Whitmore's will (October 6); General Edmund Pendleton Gaines and his wife, Lucinda, who was a first cousin of Sue Whitmore's grandmother, Frances Gaines Botts (October 12); the discomfort of having strangers live in her home, and Professor [John William] Mallet (October 16); and, the last day of "the great World's Fair," visiting St. Charles and St. Louis, Missouri (December 1). References to various topics continued in 1905: proposed road and right-of-way problems (January 11); measles epidemic at school (January 31); Gaines family genealogy (February 7, 14, 22); hassles with the estate and certain conditions (February 26); her son, Samuel Lewis Whitmore working in the Palace Shoe and Clothing Company and having conflicts with the Jewish owner (April 10); Thomas Nelson Page (1853-1922) and Professor [William] Thornton (May 11); and, Rosewell Page (1858- 1939) and William Thornton's speeches (May 24).
During September 1905 through April 1906 Harry Whitmore was at the University of Virginia. Sue Whitmore's letters to him touch upon such subjects as: Dr. [Edwin A.] Alderman delivering an address at Kable's School on November 30, the anniversary of the fire; and Geo[rge] Ben[jamin] Johnson (October 11); reading The Gift of the Morning Star by [Armistead Churchill] Gordon (October 17); Sam Whitmore being ill with malaria and "southern itch," and her enjoyment of the University of Virginia Glee Club (October 29); letter from Sam Whitmore re railroad wrecks, the possibility of statehood [for Oklahoma] and that it may be named "Sequoyah after the Author of the Cherokee alphabet" (October 31); cases of typhoid fever (November 12); a letter from Sam Whitmore concerning Carrie Nation lecturing in Missouri (November 11). Topics continued in 1906: financial problems and her interest in joining the Daughters of the Revolution and the Daughters of the Confederacy (January 23); Professor [Francis Perry] Dunnington [Analytical and Agricultural Chemistry] (January 29); attending a meeting of the Missionary Society (February 25); the situation at the Lannin Extract plant at Andrews, Cherokee County, North Carolina and an impending chemist position (March 8); interest of J[ames]; M[orris] Page in Harry Whitmore (April 2); problems with the "laboring classes" (April 12); news of the earthquake [San Francisco, California] and the burning of Leland Stanford University (April 18); and, G. W. Koiner being in Europe to induce some of the laboring classes to come to Virginia and the conflicts between capital and labor in general (May 27).
There is a break in the correspondence from June 1906 until late September 1911. During September 28, 1911 until June 18, 1912, Harry Whitmore was at Harvard University, in Cambridge, Massachusetts. Topics include farming references such as crops, labor, stock, seeding, and orchards. Letters of note or interest during 1911 include: hearing "Polk Miller and his negro quartette" (October 8); her comments on labor, "the big prices for labor have spoiled nearly all the hands, they want a fine house, plenty of money and but little work" (October 19); and, inquiries of [William Buell] Meldrum (1887-1956), a student at Harvard (November 26). Letters of interest or note during 1912 include: the "strongest fight for Woman Suffrage" now in the legislature, presentations on the rights of women by Mary Johnston (1870-1936) and Miss [Bessie Carter] Randolph (1885-1966), and Mrs. [Caro Syron] Valentine (1855- ) (January 5); a visit to the Capital in Richmond and cousin James [William] Gregory [Lt. Gov.] (1846-1912), a member of the House of Delegates (January 12); topics of the legislature including College for Women, Woman Suffrage, the Byrd Bill for the equalization of the sexes, and the prohibition bill; the presentations before the House by Mary Johnston, Miss Randolph, and Mrs. Valentine; and a scandal involving a local reverend and a married woman (February 4); the neglect of the voters and taxpayers by the present legislature and Lucy Lewin attending a training school for teachers of the hearing impaired (March 12); the death of James [William] Gregory (March 16); the million dollar bond issue for road improvement (March 24); letterhead of Sam Whitmore/House Physician/Natural Methods' Sanitarium, Asheville, NC (March 25); [William Buell] Meldrum (April 17); an outing to Congregationalist Church and Wellesley College, the sinking of the Titanic, Mary Johnston's lecture on Woman's Suffrage, and reading Johnston's The Long Roll(May 1); the marriage of Sam Whitmore and Claire Rutherford (May 26); letterhead of Sam Whitmore/Dean & Whitmore/Chiropractic Doctors/Asheville, North Carolina (June 1); and, Reel Gilkeson purchase of an automobile (June 9).
From September 29, 1912 through November 17, 1912, Harry Whitmore was at Eastern College, Manassas, Virginia. November 8 refers to the "rejoicing of the American nation over the political victory" and grief over the death of cousin Emmett H. Whitmore who shot himself with a pistol. November 17 refers to a visit by Dave Peyton, a black farmer, introducing "a colored man named Harris" and asking for a place as a farm hand.
During 1913, Harry Whitmore was in Manassas, Virginia. Sue Whitmore's letters frequently discuss activities involved in farming and news of family and friends. Topics of interest include: funeral of a Confederate veteran (January 13); letterhead of Whitmore Sanitarium (February 24); Staunton religious conference with lectures by Bishops [John Carlisle] Kilgo (1861-1922), [Collins] Denny (1854-1943), and others (March 31); Roy Whitmore being at National Cash Register which building sheltered 3,000 homeless people in Dayton, Ohio ( March 31); North River District Sunday School Convention at Parnassus on June 5th (May 15); stock being killed by lightning (May 30); historical notes on Mt. Airy and genealogical background on Major Peter Steinbergen (September 29); domestic abuse in an African-American family by husband Ben Byrd (September 29); detailed criticism of Samuel L. Whitmore's wife, Claire, and details of their marital problems and divorce (October 7-12, November 6 -11); obituary of John Franklin Templeton (October 19 & 24); legal trouble of Marshall Burton (November 2); comment on illness recovery records for whites and "colored," who have less resistance to disease (November 14); trial of [Charlie] Donaghe and question of his electrocution, being sent to an asylum, or freedom (November 24 & 27); and, the of brother John Minor Botts Gregory so many years ago (December 11).
Letters of early 1914 contain numerous references to farming, including crops and stock. Topics of interest include: Washington, D. C. tour (February 4); reference to genealogy back to George Pendleton (February 13); husband's birthday (March 15); and, [Hal D.] Flood (March 17). From Manassas, Harry Whitmore moved next to Keyser, West Virginia. Sue Whitmore's letters continue to include numerous references to farming and also mention: legal problems of hand Sam Taylor, the Burton trial taking place in October, and, rejoicing the "defeat of the whiskey men who spent hundreds of thousands of dollars to prevent prohibition" (September 24). Others topics of interest include: Reverend M[atthew]; L[aurence] Wood (1858-1932) having typhoid fever and pneumonia and a visit from Henry Dice (October 6); article re an automobile accident with four University of Virginia boys (October 6); and, postmaster, J. A. Riddle, being held responsible (by negligence) for the burglary at the Bridgewater Post Office (November 14).
During 1915, Harry Whitmore is still in Keyser, West Virginia. Topics of interest from Sue Whitmore include: Parnassus School (January 5); the [Marshall] Burton trial (January 12 & February 1); toll business on pike unsettled (January 19); [Captain T. M.] Smiley, former superintendent of county roads, statement that there are 8 toll-gates belonging to the country (January 26); decision of Charles Edgar Littlefield (1851-1915) in the equity suit of the Commonwealth of Virginia vs. the state of West Virginia (January 26); Reverend [ ] Keen's revival at Keyser (March 7); Y. M. C. A. building going up rapidly in Staunton (March 7); Samuel L. Whitmore's need for funds for tuition, state board examination, and registration of license (March 22 & April 25); the nickel looking as large as a quarter (March 22); [Henry] Dice being ill with blood poisoning (March 22 & 27); quarantine in Richmond, Winchester, and Amherst because of foot and mouth disease with horses and cattle (March 24); failure of the Augusta Sanitarium (March 27); decision of the Burton child-custody case - Mary Hess has custody and Marshall Burton has visiting rights (April 5); poll tax and right to vote in the primary and regular elections (April 25); trouble with hand Charlie and his wife Irene (May 7 & 11 & 28) and their being at Dunkard meetings nearly every night (May 24); Governor [James] McDowell to deliver address at Harry Whitmore's school (May 19); and, choosing teachers for Parnassus school (May 24); funerals of Reverend Gilbert and others (August 19); scarcity of hands to work farms (October 26); advice to sell horses in spring instead of now (November 5); and, poor showing for wheat and grass crops (December 14).
Early 1916 Harry Whitmore is still in Keyser, West Virginia, where Sue Whitmore writes concerning the farm, plowing, hauling, baling, cleaning and other activities. Other topics of interest include: Reverend [ ] Wheeler preaching locally prior to the conference (February 7); problems with R. F. D. carriers delivering on some routes because of high snow drifts and road work in the South River District causing a shortage of hands to work farms (February 18); description of Macon, Georgia, news of Sam Whitmore selling a motor truck, and news of [F. B.] Bradford Whitmore being seriously injured in a fall down an elevator shaft (March 17); missing the chance to see Helen Keller (May 19); and, needing hands but men working on the road from Spring Hill (September 28). In the fall, Harry Whitmore moves to Dallas, Texas, where he receives letters on various topics, including: slow progress on the Bridgewater bridge (October 3); problems with hiring hands to do farm work (October 3 & 11); local business and medical news (October 11); discussions of different plans to build a bridge on her farm land as well as the road plans (October-November); plans for Sue Whitmore's trip to Texas and Missouri (October-November).
During January 4 through May 19, 1917, Harry Whitmore was in Dallas, Texas, and from September 12, 1917 to December 31, 1919, and 1920-1923, he was at the College of Industrial Arts in Denton, Texas. Topics covered in these letters include personal news and news of family and friends, finances, farming business, genealogy, the American Clan Gregor Society Gathering and the Triplett family. Subjects referred to in letters of 1917 include: a newsclipping re the arrest of S. Dabney Crenshaw, Jr. for the burning of the chemical laboratory at the University of Virginia (March 3); a visit to Richmond and Mexico, Missouri (March 17, 18); a letter from Sam Whitmore concerning the automobile business slowing down because of increased prices and an additional war tax (June 27); the quarantine against infantile paralysis (September 24); and sewing for a Red Cross Society (November 15). In 1918, topics include: soldiers camped near Augusta, Georgia and soldiers going to France (February 24); the Rev. Mr. Gypsy Smith of England preaching in Staunton (April 9, May 8); and, the Spanish flu epidemic (October 20). Letters of 1919 include topics: the Baltimore Conference of the Methodist Church South in Staunton (March 23, 28); a newsclipping re John Armstrong Chaloner twenty-two years after his being declared legally insane (April 11); a newsclipping re a gift for the establishment of a School of Fine Arts at the University of Virginia from Paul G. McIntire (April 12); and, the return of hometown soldiers, Emmett Randolph and Paul Jones (July 4). Mrs. Whitmore's letters sent to Denton, Texas early 1920 discuss farm transactions and the future sale of the farm and often seek advice concerning the farm. A telegram of April 4, 1923 announces the death of Mrs. Susan Gregory Whitmore earlier that afternoon.
During July and August 1915, Harry Gregory Whitmore was traveling to California by way of the Panama Canal and returning through the Canadian Rockies. Letters to his mother from the S. S. Kroonland, Panama Pacific Line, give his initial impression of the ship and its occupants, including Louisa (Morgan) [Mrs. Herbert Livingston] Satterlee, daughter of J. Pierpont Morgan and a Miss Elizabeth A. Kittredge. Whitmore includes dates, times, coordinates, and names of places approached; he mentions Sandy Hook, Gulf Stream, St. Augustine, Key West, San Salvador, Cuba, Haiti, Caribbean Sea, Panama Canal, Col󮬠Gold Hill, Pedro Miguel Locks, Miraflores, Panama (City), Balboa, and Costa Rica. In his letter of July 24, he gives a description of the Gatun Locks. On August 21, he writes about their return route, mentioning Edmonton, Alberta, Mt. Robson, Yellowhead Pass, British Columbia, and the Grand Trunk Railway. There are also several postcards from various places.
Letters, October 1914 to August 1915, from Samuel L. Whitmore to Harry Gregory Whitmore, concern his chiropractic career, medical school, and divorce. Initially, Whitmore is with Elvin Wheeler, Doctor of Chiropractic, in Atlanta, Georgia, while attending lectures at the Georgia College of Medicine and Surgery. In October 1914, he relates the effects of the cotton crisis on all business, referring to reduced work forces and cut wages, resulting in doctors not being paid for services. He also mentions taking orders for Aluminum Cooking Utensils to supplement wages and Asa G. Candler's financial involvement in the medical college. On November 20, 1914, he discusses the situation with the medical school and courses, his financial status, marriage problems and divorce, and possible sales representative work with the Reo Automobile Company; and comments on hearing Congressman Champ Clark (1850-1921). In December 1914, he relates news of his divorce, medical situation, financial status, appeal of the sanitarium as a place to practice medicine, and the current doctor situation, mentioning a few of the prominent doctors and their financial situations, stating that "the most that you get out of doctoring is reputation." He also mentions the situation with the Reo Automobile Company, and the fact that it is the largest financial concern in the auto business. In January 1915, he discusses his sensational divorce, plans for filing divorce, and the claims filed in Claire Whitmore's divorce petition; a newspaper clipping on the divorce is included. He also discusses the situation at the Georgia College of Medicine and Surgery following standards being raised by the Carnegie Foundation and the American Medical Association. He relates that he has been attending medical course lectures, and his plans to complete his medical education and then take the Florida State Board examinations. In February and March, he needs money for tuition and other fees involved in dissection, graduation, the state board exam, and registration of license. In April, Whitmore refers to the rigid examination of the Florida State Board of Medical Examiners, listing subject examinations, giving progress on his examinations. He details his medical studies and career plans, mentions a gift from the class to president D. H. Griffith and his presentation. During May, his case is before the Trustees concerning the legalities of bestowing a medical diploma on him. He is also considering a sales position at the Reo Motor Car Company in order to make some money as doctors are having a hard time collecting debts for services. On June 15, Whitmore writes that the Trustees 'passed' upon the Seniors and that he is having to meet with each one; mentions meetings with board members D. F. Johnson and John Green and their comments; and writes that the opinion is that they can graduate him legally but are not sure if it is the right thing to do. He also relates the direction of plans with Reo Motor Car Company. A letter of July 14 comments on Harry Gregory Whitmore's extensive trip to California and its educational value and the picture show, Marse Covington, set in Essex County, Virginia. There is a letter, 1920, to Whitmore from M. B. Whitmore concerning his father's farm. There are also obituaries for Samuel L. Whitmore from July 1941.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Susan Gregory Whitmore to Harry Gregory Whitmore 1900-1904, 11 folders (Box 1)
  - Susan Gregory Whitmore to Harry Gregory Whitmore 1905-1912, 11 folders (Box 2)
  - Susan Gregory Whitmore to Harry Gregory Whitmore 1913-1916, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - Susan Gregory Whitmore to Harry Gregory Whitmore 1917-1920, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Harry Gregory Whitmore to Susan Gregory Whitmore re Trip to California 1915 Jul-Aug (Box 4)
  - Samuel L. Whitmore to Harry Gregory Whitmore, and related (1914-1915) 1941 (Box 4)